Are you ready to power up your English? Today, we're going to unlock some super special words that,
英語をパワーアップする準備はできていますか？ 今日は特別な言葉を紹介します。
honestly, they just break all the normal rules. If you can master these, you're going to sound
これらの言葉は普通のルールを破ります。 これをマスターすれば、もっと自然に聞こえます。
so much more natural. Let's do this. So, first off, a quick question for you.
さあ、始めましょう。まずは簡単な質問です。
Think about your class at school. Who's the fastest runner? Who's the funniest? Or,
学校のクラスを思い出してみてください。 誰が一番速く走りますか？誰が一番面白いですか？
who's the best at video games? See, to answer questions like these,
または、誰がゲームが得意ですか？ こういった質問に答えるには、
you need the special words we're diving into today.
今日学ぶ特別な言葉が必要です。
So, let's say you want to say, my friend is a good singer.
例えば、「私の友達は歌が上手です」と言いたいとします。
That sentence is perfect. But, what if you want to compare?
その文は完璧です。でも、比較したい場合はどうでしょう？
You might think, logically, that she is gooder than you.
「彼女はあなたより上手」と考えるかもしれません。
Makes sense, right? But, and this is a big but,
理にかなっていますよね？でも、これは大きな間違いです。
that's a super common mistake.
英語では、単にERを加えるだけではありません。
Some words in English don't just add ER.
特別なパワーアップがあるのです。
They have these secret power-ups, just like in a video game.
まるでビデオゲームのように。
So, in this explainer,
では、この説明で、
we are going to learn all about these special rules. We're going to see how some words totally
これらの特別なルールを学びましょう。 いくつかの言葉がどのように変わるか見ていきます。
transform when we use them to compare stuff. So for these words, you can just forget about
これらの言葉では、urやestを忘れて大丈夫です。 それらはこの言葉には似合いません。
ur and est. They are way too cool for that. Okay, let's kick things off with a big talent show
さて、大きな才能ショーを始めましょう。 一方には「good」、もう一方には「well」がいます。
showdown. In one corner, we have the word good. And in the other corner, we've got the word well.
似ているように見えますが、役割は全く異なります。 さあ、見てみましょう。まずはジャニスです。
Now, they might seem kind of similar, but trust me, they have very different jobs.
文は「ジャニスは歌が上手です」と言っています。
Let's see how they do. First up, let's meet Janice.
ここで「good」はジャニスを説明しています。
The sentence says, Janice is a good singer.
具体的には、彼女がどんな歌手かを示しています。
So here the word good is describing Janice.
「Good」は形容詞で、人や場所、
More specifically, it's telling us what kind of singer she is.
物を説明する役割があります。 とてもシンプルですね。
Good is what we call an adjective, and its job is just to describe a person, a place,
でも、友達のリンダが競技に参加したらどうなるでしょう？
or a thing. Pretty simple, right?
今は二人を比較しています。 「good」とは言えません。
But wait, what happens when her friend Linda jumps into the competition?
代わりに「good」は最初のパワーアップを得て「better」になります。
Now we're comparing two people, and we can't say good or no way.
「ジャニスはリンダより歌が上手です」と言います。
Instead, Good gets its first power-up and transforms into better.
一人を別の人と比較しています。
So we say, Janice is a better singer than Linda.
そして、最終ラウンドです。
We're comparing one person against another.
ジャニスは学校中の全員と対戦します。
And now for the final round.
彼女が一番だと言うために、「good」は
Janice is up against everyone in the whole school.
究極のパワーアップを使わなければなりません。
So to say she's number one, Good has to use its ultimate power-up.
そして「the best」になります。ジャニスが一番の歌手です。 これが最終形態です。
And it becomes the best. Janice is the best singer of all. This is it.
覚えておいてください。「good」、「better」、「the best」です。
The top level. The final evolution.
さて、次の参加者、ビリーを呼びましょう。
remember, good, better, the best.
このスライドには「ビリーはピアノを上手に弾きます」と書いてあります。
Alright, let's bring out our next contestant, Billy.
ここで注意が必要です。 ビリー自身を説明していますか？
This slide says, Billy plays the piano well.
うーん、そうではありません。 彼の演奏方法を説明しています。
Now, pay close attention here. Are we describing Billy himself?
「well」は動作、つまり「弾く」を説明しているので、 「well」は副詞です。
Hmm, not really. We're describing how he plays.
でも、彼の友達ジョンが演奏し始めたらどうなりますか？
The word well describes the action, the verb plays, so well is an adverb.
彼らを比較する必要があります。 ここからが本当に面白くなります。
But what happens when his buddy John starts playing too?
「well」も「better」に変わります。 「good」と同じように。
We need to compare them. And here's where it gets really interesting.
「ビリーはジョンよりピアノを上手に弾きます」。
it out. Well, also transforms into better, just like Good did.
同じパワーアップですが、出発点が異なります。
Billy plays the piano better than John.
次は何か分かりますよね。
It's the same power-up, just from a different starting word.
ビリーを学校の他の全員と比較すると、 「well」は究極のパワーアップを使います。
When we compare Billy to everyone else in the school, Well uses its ultimate power- up
そう、やっぱり「the best」になります。
to become, you got it, the best.
ビリーは学校で一番ピアノが上手です。
Billy plays the piano the best in his school.
「good」と同じ素晴らしいパワーアップを持っています。
It shares the exact same awesome power-ups as Good.
ここで覚えておくべきことは、
So here's the main thing you gotta remember.
「good」は形容詞で、人や物を説明します。 「well」は副詞で、動作を説明します。
is an adjective. It describes people and things. Well is an adverb. It describes actions. They
役割は異なりますが、比較が必要なときは、 どちらも「better」と「the best」にレベルアップします。
have different jobs, for sure. But when it's game time, when you need to compare, they
さて、才能ショーは終了です。 次の新しい挑戦の時間です。
both level up to better and the best.
学校祭に行って、 食べ物のコンテストをしましょう。
Okay, the talent show is over. Time for a totally new challenge. Let's head on over
ここで次の特別な言葉を学びます。「many」と「much」です。
to the school festival for an eating contest. This is where we're going to learn our
このコンテストを始める前に、 知っておくべきルールがあります。
next set of special words, many versus much.
英語では、 数えられるものがあります。クッキーやホットドッグのように。
You can literally count them, one, two, three.
実際に数えられるよ、1、2、3。
But other things are uncountable, like tea, water, or rice.
でも、茶や水、米のように数えられないものもある。
You can't really count the liquid itself, right?
液体自体は数えられないよね？
You count the cups or the bottles.
カップやボトルを数えるんだ。
This difference is super, super important for our next two words.
この違いは、次の2つの単語にとって非常に重要だよ。
First up is Bob, and he is going to town on those cookies.
まずはボブが、クッキーを食べまくっている。
Now, can you count cookies? Yep, you sure can.
クッキーは数えられるよね？もちろん。
So for things we can count, we use the word many.
数えられるものには「many」を使う。
Bob ate too many cookies. But hold on, here comes John.
ボブはクッキーを食べすぎた。でも、ジョンが来たよ。
It's a competition now.
今、競争が始まった。
To compare the number of cookies these two ate, many gets a power-up.
この2人が食べたクッキーの数を比べると、「many」はパワーアップする。
It transforms into more. So we say, Bob ate more cookies than John.
「more」に変わる。だから、ボブはジョンより多くのクッキーを食べた。
And to win the family championship, Bob's gonna need that ultimate power-up.
家族チャンピオンシップを勝ち取るには、ボブは究極のパワーアップが必要だ。
For the largest number of countable things, many becomes the most.
数えられるものの最大数では、「many」は「most」になる。
Bob ate the most cookies in his family. He is the champion.
ボブは家族の中で最も多くのクッキーを食べた。彼がチャンピオンだ。
Okay, let's switch over to the drink station. Janice is back.
さて、飲み物のコーナーに移ろう。ジャニスが戻ってきた。
This time, Janice drank too much tea. Can you count tea?
今回は、ジャニスが茶を飲みすぎた。茶は数えられる？
Nope, it's a liquid, it's uncountable.
いいえ、液体だから数えられない。
And that's exactly why we use the word much.
だから「much」を使うんだ。
And look, Linda's here too.
ほら、リンダも来てる。
So when we compare them, guess what happens?
彼女たちを比べると、どうなると思う？
Much also powers up to more, just like many did.
「much」も「more」にパワーアップする、まるで「many」のように。
Janice drank more tea than Linda.
ジャニスはリンダより多くの茶を飲んだ。
And you guessed it, the ultimate power up here is also the most.
そして、究極のパワーアップも「most」だ。
It's another one of those awesome shared power-ups.
これは素晴らしい共有パワーアップの一つだ。
Okay, you've seen all the words in action, you've seen them compete,
さて、すべての単語を見てきたし、競争も見た。
and now it's time for the big reveal.
今は大発表の時だ。
Let's put everything we've just learned together
これまで学んだことをまとめよう。
on one ultimate cheat sheet. This is like the secret code
これはネイティブの英語話者のように聞こえるための秘密のコードだ。
to sounding like a native English speaker. Take a look.
見てみて。
This chart makes everything super clear.
このチャートはすべてを明確に示している。
You can see the pattern, right?
パターンが見えるよね？
Good and well start off as different words,
「good」と「well」は異なる言葉で始まるが、
but then bam, they both power up to better and the best.
その後、両方とも「better」と「best」にパワーアップする。
And the exact same thing happens with many and much.
「many」と「much」も同じことが起こる。
They both level up to more and the most.
両方とも「more」と「most」にレベルアップする。
So they start in different places,
だから、異なる場所から始まるが、
but they end up sharing the same power- ups.
同じパワーアップを共有することになる。
All right, you've seen the rules,
さて、ルールを見てきたし、
and now you have the ultimate cheat sheet.
究極のチートシートも手に入れた。
So it's your turn to be the champion.
さあ、あなたがチャンピオンになる番だ。
Let's see if you've really mastered these special rules
これらの特別なルールを本当にマスターしたか、
with a quick little quiz. You ready? Here we go, first question.
簡単なクイズで確認してみよう。準備はいい？さあ、最初の質問。
Janus sings blank, then Linda. Hmm, think about it.
ジャニスは「blank」、リンダより歌う。うーん、考えてみて。
Are we describing Janice, the person,
私たちはジャニスという人を説明しているのか、
or are we describing how she sings, the action?
それとも彼女の歌い方、行動を説明しているのか？
And we're comparing two people,
2人を比べているから、
so what word do you think goes in that blend?
その「blank」に入る言葉は何だと思う？
And the answer is better, yes! We are describing the action sings,
答えは「better」。そう！行動「sings」を説明しているから、
so our base word as well. And because we're comparing her to Linda,
基本の単語もそうなる。そして、リンダと比べているから、
it powers up to better, you got it, excellent job.
「better」にパワーアップする。よくできたね。
You've totally got the secret code now.
もう秘密のコードを完全に理解したね。
You know how to say someone is better, or has more,
誰かが「better」だとか「more」を言ったり、
or is simply the best. So my final question for you is this,
単に「the best」と言ったりする方法がわかる。最後の質問はこれだ。
who will you say is the best at something?
誰が何かで一番だと言える？
Go on, try using one of these awesome power-up words today.
さあ、今日この素晴らしいパワーアップの言葉を使ってみて。
Thanks for hanging out with me.
一緒にいてくれてありがとう。